A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Frank Lappin Horsfall, Jr. FA822
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Frank Lappin Horsfall, Jr.
1934-1960
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
Horsfall, Frank Lappin
FA822
0.44 Cubic Feet 1 box
2 boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
The newly adopted By-Laws of 1953 provided for an elected Vice-President who was a member of the Board of Trustees. Thomas Milton Rivers was elected the first Vice-President of the newly constituted Board of Trustees and served as Director of The Institute, Director of the Department of Laboratories and Director of the Hospital until his retirement in 1955.
August 1955 amendments to the By-Laws abolished the elected Vice-President and the requirement which provided that he be a member of the Board of Trustees and called for one or more appointed Vice-Presidents. Further amendment, January 25, 1956 provided that the Board of Trustees elect one or more Vice-Presidents to discharge such functions as may be assigned to them by the President or by resolution duly accepted at any meeting.
Between 1955 and 1959 Frank Lappin Horsfall, Jr. held the position of Vice-President for Clinical Studies; between 1955 and 1964 Douglas Whitaker served as Vice-President for Administration (between 1961-64 changed to Vice-President for Academic Administration). In 1964/65 Maclyn McCarty was elected Vice-President with special responsibilities in the clinical sciences. He is at the same time, Physician-in-Chief. In 1965 Carl Pfaffmann was elected Vice-President and Professor to develop a program of research and graduate instruction in the behavioral and social sciences. In 1969/70 a third Vice-President was added. This position carries with it the role of Secretary to the Board of Trustees and was filled by Charles Eugene Sunderlin.
In 1972 the University trustees elected Rodney W. Nichols to a new post of Vice-President for Program planning. He had been the first Director of the Office of Program Planning and Development.
In 1973 Albert Gold was named Vice-President for Academic Resources. As Vice-President he also retains his responsibilities relating to Junior faculty (Director of Postdoctoral Affairs) with additional duties in connection with organization, operation and planning at the University.
In 1974, effective September 15, Maclyn McCarty retired as Physician-in-Chief of the Hospital, which post was then filled by Dr. Attalah Kappas.
June 30, 1976 Eugene Sunderlin retired as vice-president of the RU.
June 1978 Dr. Albert Gold resigned from the University and October 1978 Drs. McCarty and Pfaffmann having reached retirement age resigned their positions as Vice-President. Mr. Rodney Nichols was elected to a new position of executive Vice-President and Mr. David J. Lyons was elected to a new position as Vice-President and Controller with new managerial responsibilities.
Other Finding Aids
FA903 Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Frank Lappin Horsfall, Jr., Subject Files, Series 4
Arrangement
Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Frank Lappin Horsfall, Jr is arranged in 3 series:
Series 2: Administrative Correspondence. Series 4: Subject Files. Series 6: Biographical Material.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 342-2 and I 342-6
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Vice President, 1955-1959
Scope and Contents
This finding aid contains administrative correspondence and biographical material.
- Administrative correspondence, 1942-1960; 2; 5 folders
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in alphabetical and chronological order
  File Plan note
  Former Classification: I 342-2
  - Administrative correspondence, 1942-1960 (Box 1)
  - Cohn, Alfred Einstein, 1957 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Obituary material written by Frank L. Horsfall, Jr.
  - McCarty, Maclyn, 1945-1951 (Box 1)
    Primarily copies of recommendations for awards or memberships made by F.L. Horsfall, Jr.
  - Applications for staff appointments with letters of recommendation (Box 1)
    Appointments are for staff appointment or appointments as visiting investigators Barbarossa, Carlo, Blomstrand, Rolf Lennart, Böhme, Diethelm H., Bouvier, Claude A., Elsbach, Peter, Fascoli, Angelo, James, A.T., Kavanau, Julian Lee, Korn, Martin W., Nemes, Marjorie Mary, Newton, Alison Anne, Overman, John Reagan, Rieben, William, Robbins, Elliot, Rzucidlo, Ludwik T., Sturman, Martin Frank, Trautman, Rodes, Vesell, Elliot Saul.
    Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Miscellaneous appointment notifications and biographical information (Box 1)
    Bennett, Dorothea, Chang, Hsiang-Tung, DeLuca, Chester, Harrison, Ross Granville, Johnson, Charles W., Kao, Cheng-yuan, Paul, John Rodman, Rosenbaum, Robert M., Singer, Ira.
- Biographical material, 1934-1960; 6; 1 folder; 3 volumes
  Arranged in chronological order.
  Former Classification: I 342-6
  - Biographical material
    - Application and recommendation for staff appointment, 1934 (Box 1)
    - Photographs (Box 1)
    - Curriculum vitae with memberships (Box 1)
    - Autobiographical essay written at request of Dr. Gasser (Box 1)
    - Correspondence relating to appointment at Institute and Navy Service during W.W. II, 1941-1955 (Box 1)
    - Letters of congratulation on appointment as Vice-President of Institute and Physician-in-Chief, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Bibliography, 1930-1960 (Box 1)
  - Collected reprints, 3 volumes